<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>wordpress | Matthew Daly&apos;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/categories/wordpress/</link>
    <updated>2015-07-19T11:30:41Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Matthew Daly</name>
        <email>matthew@matthewdaly.co.uk</email>
        <uri>http://matthewdaly.co.uk</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/categories/wordpress/"/>
    <subtitle>wordpress | I&apos;m a web developer in Norfolk. This is my blog...</subtitle>
    <rights>Matthew Daly 2015</rights>
    <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dumping WordPress for Octopress]]></title>
        <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2012/05/31/dumping-wordpress-for-octopress/</id>
        <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2012/05/31/dumping-wordpress-for-octopress/">
        </link>
        <updated>2012-05-31T20:25:00Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I’ve gotten more and more fed up with WordPress as a blogging platform. It’s certainly a great content management system, and for non-technical bloggers it’s absolutely perfect, but I’ve been increasingly finding myself hitting barriers that make it harder than it should be to get stuff done. It’s just not the best platform for blogging about web development.</p>
<p>Take my recent series of Django tutorials, for example. You wouldn’t believe the amount of time I spent trying to format some of the code properly in TinyMCE for those. Furthermore, the end result, even though the theme was a custom one I’d built myself that was somewhat optimised for showing off code, wasn’t exactly great.</p>
<p>In my opinion, Markdown is a far better option for writing blog posts in than using a rich text editor like TinyMCE. You normally have a pretty good idea what the end results will look like, and it’s generally well-formatted HTML. Also, it means I can easily write my blog posts in Vim.</p>
<p>Octopress was therefore an obvious choice. It’s absolutely brilliant for sharing code - compared to WordPress, code samples look <em>stunning</em>. Also, because it generates static HTML, it loads an awful lot faster than WordPress does, and the default theme is extremely nice. So that’s what I’ve gone for.</p>
<p>The only issue is that my web host are a bit funny about offering SSH access, so I’ve resorted to FTP-ing the files across, which isn’t ideal. Still, it’s not that big an issue, and I’ll have to see how it goes with Octopress. I do have a low-end VPS I could point this domain name at instead and run it from there if necessary, so I can always resort to that if this is too cumbersome.</p>
]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[New theme]]></title>
        <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2012/02/28/new-theme/</id>
        <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2012/02/28/new-theme/">
        </link>
        <updated>2012-02-28T18:25:30Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a long time now, I’ve kept meaning to write my own WordPress theme from scratch for this site, but just haven’t been able to find the time to do so. Now, I’ve finally found the time to do so, and here it is!</p>
<p>Please let me know what you think, but be gentle (this is my first solo WordPress theme, and also the only one I’ve built completely from scratch), and if you find any issues with it please let me know. Don’t expect it to look great in IE6 or IE7 however - I’ve given it a very cursory review in those browsers, and that’s all. It’s still perfectly readable, but it uses a fair amount of CSS3 so it’s inevitably not going to look as pretty in those browsers.</p>
<p>The code is <a href="https://github.com/matthewbdaly/Steel-Age">on GitHub</a> if you want to take a look.</p>
]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[New hosting]]></title>
        <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2010/05/10/new-hosting/</id>
        <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2010/05/10/new-hosting/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-05-09T23:52:53Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve now gone and switched to paid hosting, and have dumped the old static site in favour of a Wordpress-powered blog on my own domain. I’ve found Wordpress to be an extremely flexible and powerful solution, far superior to Blogger, and I’m really excited about the possibilities of a self-hosted blog, so I’m really looking forward to establishing myself here! At some point I intend to create a custom theme of my own, but for now this one will do fine!</p>
<p>As I mentioned previously, I’ve changed the emphasis of the blog towards web development. I’ve also now made a number of other improvements - comments are now powered by Disqus, to facilitate easier sharing of posts and making it easier for people to reply to me via blog posts of their own.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></summary>
    </entry>
</feed>