<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: yeoman | Matthew Daly's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/categories/yeoman/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-09T20:33:50+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Daly]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing generator-simple-static-blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2014/10/05/introducing-generator-simple-static-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-05T19:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2014/10/05/introducing-generator-simple-static-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a big fan of static site generators. I ditched WordPress for Octopress over two years ago because it was free to host on GitHub Pages and much faster, had much better syntax highlighting, and I liked being able to write posts in Vim, and I&rsquo;ve never looked back since.</p>

<p>That said, Octopress is written in Ruby, a language I&rsquo;ve never been that keen on. Ideally I&rsquo;d prefer to use Python or JavaScript, but none of the solutions I&rsquo;ve found have been to my liking. Recently I&rsquo;ve been using Grunt and Yeoman to some extent, and I&rsquo;ve wondered about the idea of creating a Yeoman generator to build a static blogging engine. After discovering <code>grunt-markdown-blog</code>, I took the plunge and have built a simple blog generator called <a href="https://github.com/matthewbdaly/generator-simple-static-blog">generator-simple-static-blog</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve published it to NPM, so feel free to check it out. It includes code highlighting with the Zenburn colour scheme by default (although highlight.js includes many other themes, so just switch to another one if you want), and it should be easy to edit the templates. I&rsquo;ve also included the ability to deploy automatically to GitHub Pages using Grunt.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t anticipate moving over to this from Octopress for the foreseeable future, but it&rsquo;s been an interesting project for the weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My first Yeoman generator]]></title>
    <link href="http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-yeoman-generator/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T11:38:40+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://matthewdaly.co.uk/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-yeoman-generator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At work I use the <a href="http://www.getskeleton.com/">Skeleton boilerplate</a> a lot - my boss, who handles most of the design work, likes it and generally uses it for his designs. I&rsquo;ve also been using <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">Grunt</a> a lot lately, so it was inevitable that I&rsquo;d probably start to look for a <a href="http://yeoman.io/">Yeoman</a> generator for working with it.</p>

<p>There was an existing Yeoman generator for Skeleton, but it didn&rsquo;t really do what I wanted. I wanted something that:</p>

<ul>
<li>Included jQuery and Modernizr</li>
<li>Automatically concatenates and minifies all the JavaScript and CSS</li>
<li>Will automatically rebuild on changes</li>
<li>Includes LiveReload and a development server</li>
<li>Includes automatic deployment via FTP</li>
</ul>


<p>After looking through the documentation for Yeoman, it was actually quick and easy to throw together my own generator and put it up. It&rsquo;s available <a href="https://npmjs.org/package/generator-skellington">here</a>, and the GitHub repository is <a href="https://github.com/matthewbdaly/generator-skellington">here</a>.</p>

<p>Future plans for it include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adding auto-prefixing for CSS</li>
<li>Removing redundant CSS rules automatically</li>
<li>Possibly, alternate deployment methods</li>
</ul>


<p>Frustratingly, NPM seems to be playing up at present - it&rsquo;s not picking up the README file, and the Yeoman site isn&rsquo;t pulling it in. Any idea why, anyone?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
